# 哈喽大家好
Hello!
# 今天我用这个泡了五斤米
Today I have soaked 5 Jin (2.5kg) of rice.
# 五斤桂朝米
This is Guichao Rice.
# 然后昨晚上泡的
They have been soaked overnight.
# 今天给我四伯爷做一个小时候的味道 凉糕
I will make a childhood dish, cold rice cake, for my uncle.
# 现在这个天气热得不得了
Today is very hot.
# 我四伯爷今天卖了肉回来
My uncle has just came back from the butchery.
# 等一下我弄来冻到冰箱里面
We can put some meat into the freezer afterwards.
# 要的啊
Sure.
# 天气太大了
It is way to hot today.
# 泡好了就用这个机子来打
We will actually use this machine to mill the rice.
# 把它打出来
Using a machine
# 其实我们用这个打比石磨推要快得多
is way faster than using a stone mill.
# 因为这个不像豆花儿不像黄豆
Since those are not soy beans
# 黄豆当然是用那个石磨磨 磨得更好
that require the use of stone mill
# 因为越细越好
to create a better and smoother texture,
# 这个的话是机器更省力
using machine on rice is much more efficient.
# 来嘛
Let's do it.
# 多了打2次就是
We can mill it several times.
# 嗯 可以
That looks good.
# 好啦 这个已经磨完了
Now we have finished milling the rice.
# 要是传统做法的话可能要磨个两个小时吧
It might cost about two hours using a traditional mill.
# 要一两个小时
One or two hours.
# 这个特别的快
But this is really fast.
# 我们现在把这个给它弄出来
Now we will pour those out,
# 因为底下有一层
because the bottom layer
# 有一点点粗
is a little thicker.
# 走嘛 我把这个洗哈洗了来
Let's clean this up.
# 这哈咋个整
What do we do with the rice milk?
# 熬了撒就可以
You just steam it.
# 机子你弄来洗了
Are you going to clean the machine as well?
# 啊 洗了 洗了之后我煮那个石灰水
Yes, and I will boil the whitewash afterwards.
# 我没干过 我清不到
I have never done this before so I can't help.
# 不关事
It is fine.
# 我吃倒是吃过
But I have eaten it before.
# 好啦 我们这个水已经烧开了
Ok, this water is boiling.
# 石灰水烧开了之后让它再沉淀一下
We will let it subside for a while after boiling.
# 沉淀完了之后把这个渣去掉
After that, we will clean up the residues.
# 去掉了之后再把它烧开
Then boil it again.
# 然后就把这个米浆可以倒进去
Now we are ready to pour the rice milk in.
# 先搅
Stir.
# 搅到它适合的浓稠度了之后
After mixing to the right thickness,
# 再把它倒出来然后凉了之后就变成了凉糕
pour the mixture out and it will turn into rice cake.
# 你看像我们这个上面飘的这个东西啊
You see those things that are floating around.
# 其实它是因为空气
It because of air
# 进去了就发生了一个反应
getting in and starting a reaction.
# 现在我们把它煮开了之后就让它沉淀
We will let it subside after boiling.
# 等一下面上这里会有一层 把它舀来扔掉
Later on, there will be a layer of residues at the surface, which we will get rid of.
# 然后下面的那一层也不要 我们只要中间的水
There will be another layer at the bottom which we also don't need. We only need the whitewash in the middle.
# 待会儿沉淀好了我们再来煮凉糕
We will wait for a little while before we pour in the rice milk.
# 现在开始熬红糖
Now let's prepare the brown sugar.
# 然后我们把这个红糖切碎
We need to cut up the brown sugar.
# 红糖的比例就是2斤糖 1斤多一点的水
The ratio is: 2 Jin(1kg) of brown sugar with 1 Jin(0.5kg) of water.
# 如果水放太多了的话就稀一点
It will be too watery if you add to much water.
# 当然不喜欢吃太甜的可以多放水
However, you can certainly add more water if you don't like it to be overly sweet.
# 好啦 我们把这里切好了就可以熬糖浆了
Okay, now we are ready to make the syrup.
# 慢点的
Slowly.
# 慢点慢点 慢点 四伯爷不要慌嘛
Slowly, uncle don't panic.
# 太快了的话一哈就
It's bad to go too fast.
# 这种凉糕硬是拷的 尽是用拷
This kind of rice cake is made by mixing everything together.
# 还要拷快点诶
You need to mix faster.
# 这个还有技术的 拷太快溅起来烫到人不得了
This is actually a skill, if you mix it too fast the mixture will spatter out.
# 拷慢了这下面就糟了 粘锅
However, if you do it too slowly the mixture will stick to the bottom of the wok.
# 好好好 四伯爷先不倒了
Okay, uncle that is enough.
# 不能倒了
We can't pour in anymore.
# 好啦 我们这个按照比例已经做出来了
Okay, we have followed the right ratio.
# 这个还多白
This is pretty white.
# 嗯
Yes.
# 现在我们把它再煮一会儿
Now let's boil it for a little longer.
# 好啦 现在我们已经搞出来
Okay, we are done.
# 我们都满头大汗
We are sweating already.
# 因为现在又是三伏天 热得不得了
It is really hot recently.
# 一次性做这么多
I made so much rice cake at once.
# 等会儿叫乡亲邻里过来一起吃
I will let my neighbors to try it.
# 你看这个效果非常的棒
You see this looks quite decent.
# 这个木头盒子是跟我师傅借的
I borrowed this wooden box from my master.
# 跟他借来用一下
Borrowed from him.
# 我小时候就是他们就是用的这个
When I was a kid, they used to carry those boxes with rice cake
# 把它划成一块一块的挑着来卖
and slice them into chunks to sell.
# 这一次做的就相当于是小时候的味道了
This time I am tasting my childhood.
# 这里可能有50斤
There might be 50 Jin(25kg) right here.
# 50斤啊
50 Jin(25 kg)?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 差不多四五十斤
About 40 Jin(20kg) to 50 Jin(25kg).
# 我们这个凉糕已经做了有
It's been
# 放了十几个小时了吧
more than ten hours.
# 嗯
Yea.
# 是十多个小时
About ten hours.
# 是昨天下午做的
We made this yesterday afternoon.
# 然后今天又放了一会儿
Until right now,
# 到现在目前为止有15个小时左右了
I guess it has been 15 hours.
# 然后我跟我师父借了这个
And I have also borrowed this from my master.
# 直接这样比起来
We will line it up like this.
# 直接这样子
And just
# 一划一划
slice it.
# 干起撒 划撒
Let's do it.
# 划来干起 要得
Yea!
# 老子想吃得很了
I want to try this so bad.
# 开始划了 四伯爷
I am starting, uncle.
# 抵着这个（竹片）哈 不要挨着那个
I need to line up with this piece of bamboo.
# 好
Yes.
# 这个还就是要划快一点 划慢了还不得行
I need to slice it quickly.
# 嗯
Yes.
# 划慢了要划烂
I will ruin the shape if I slice it too slowly.
# 又打湿哈水
Dip this in water.
# 这哈竖着来
Let's do it this way.
# 有点大坨了噶
That looks kind of big.
# 好啦 现在我们这个已经划出来了
Now we have slice out the chunks.
# 但是要先淋点水上去才好(分开）
But we still need to pour water
# 才好把它弄出来
in order to separate them.
# 可能这一块会烂
This one might break.
# 不用（碗）我把它放这里面
Let's put this in here.
# 放那里面冷着啊
Let it cools down.
# 放冰水里把它冰着
Put this in ice water.
# 看
Look.
# 哇
Wow.
# 来了火的
Looks good.
# 好安逸
Nice.
# 还合适的很安
That looks really nice.
# 它还要跑
It kind of wiggles around.
# 不关事
No big deal.
# 伯爷先来嘛
Uncle, you try it first.
# 要的 我先欣赏哈
Sure, let me try it.
# 你给他数着嘛 看他吃得了几碗
You need to count and see how many bowls he can eat.
# 安逸
So nice.
# 哦哟 好大一碗的哦
Wow, this a big bowl.
# 快点哦 我这碗没得了
You gotta be fast, I am almost finished.
# 沺沺 来吃凉糕了
Tiantian, come to eat rice cake.
# 沺沺过来
Come here.
# 没有调羹（勺子）
I don't have a spoon though.
# 喊爷爷再吃一碗
Call your grandpa to eat another bowl.
# 我都吃完了这一碗
I have already finished this one.
# 再来一碗 你说爷爷再吃一碗
One more, say this to your grandpa.
# 这凉糕我伯爷吃了三块
My uncle has already eaten three chunks of rice cake.
# 可能有三斤多
About 1.5kg.
# 我伯娘也吃了两碗多了
And my aunt has eaten two chunks.
# 我还又在吃
I am still eating as well.
# 我这是第二碗
This is my second chunk.
# 这都是第四碗上了
It's already my fourth bowl.
# 吃是挺好吃的
It's really tasty.
# 就是怎么说呢 做这个有点麻烦
But this rice cake is kind of tedious to make.
# 成本是很低
It doesn't cost much money,
# 时间成本比较高
but a lot of time.
# 又不散 又嫩 又绵扎
This is firm, tender, and smooth.
# 嗯
Yea.
# 夹得起来 看
I can pick it up with my chopsticks, see.
# 夹得起来 又嫩
It's really tender.
# 吃凉糕就是要这样子 嫩很了的不好吃
This is a good rice cake. Those that are way too tender aren't good.
# 嫩很了要用勺子的不好吃
To the point that you need a spoon to eat it.
# 就这样夹来吃
It's good to eat it like this with chopsticks.
# 嗯
Yes.
# 好啦 本期视频就到这里 拜拜
Okay, this is it for this video. See you!
# 拜拜
Bye!
# 我吃了四大碗
Four bowls.
# 拜拜
Bye!
# 我吃了三碗了这碗吃了
I have eaten three bowls already.
# 吃了四大碗
Four bowls.
# 真的好吃
It's so good.